<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title></title>
        <description>Intended as a documentation theme based on Jekyll for technical writers documenting software and other technical visualizations, this theme has all the elements you would need to handle multiple visualizations with both multi-level sidebar navigation, tags, and other documentation features.</description>
        <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 19:34:53 -0400</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 19:34:53 -0400</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
        
        <item>
            <title>Censored state data scientist launches Florida COVID-19 dashboard independently</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Rebekah Jones managed the Florida COVID-19 dashboard until she tried to add a feature to show which counties comply with the reopening criteria.  Now you can see what got her fired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones was the &lt;mark&gt;original architect of the dashboard&lt;/mark&gt; that was hailed by Dr. Birx from the White House Coronavirus Task Force as one of the best in the country.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#floridapolitics:birx-dashboard&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  She made a different kind of news in May when the Florida Department of Health &lt;mark&gt;removed her from her post&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#floridatoday:rebekah-jones-sidelined&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; after reprimanding her for making unauthorized public statements.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#cbslocalmiami:jones-fired-for-public-statements&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her supervisor has reported that the incident that led to her removal was specifically about the “EventDate” data, the self-reported date that a patient remembers first developing symptoms.  This kind of information can be useful for the kind of timing analysis that researchers like Steve McConnell are using to provide &lt;a href=&quot;https://stevemcconnell.com/covid/covid-19-information-center-state-data/&quot;&gt;open-readiness reports&lt;/a&gt; at the state level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones released a &lt;a href=&quot;https://geojones.org/2020/05/22/public-statement/&quot;&gt;public statement&lt;/a&gt; saying that the issue was that she &lt;mark&gt;refused &quot;to manually change data in a misleading way&lt;/mark&gt; to drum up public support of resuming pre-pandemic level of activities without a &lt;mark&gt;science-based assessment of each county’s respective risk or readiness&lt;/mark&gt; to do so.”&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#rebehakjones:response-to-media&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
If refusing to mislead the public during a health crisis is insubordination then I will wear that badge with honor.
&lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Rebekah Jones(missing reference)&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-florida-ready-to-reopen&quot;&gt;Is Florida ready to reopen?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 Task Force at the State of Florida announced in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flgov.com/wp-content/uploads/covid19/Taskforce%20Report.pdf&quot;&gt;Plan for Florida’s Recovery&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;mark&gt;Florida would follow the &lt;i&gt;White House Guidelines for Opening up America Again&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/mark&gt; as a baseline for reopening.  That plan requires &lt;mark&gt;satisfying three benchmarks&lt;/mark&gt; before reopening:&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#florida:plan-for-floridas-recovery&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A downward trajectory of influenza-like illnesses (ILI) &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; a downward trajectory of COVID-19-like illnesses (fever, cough, shortness of breath)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A downward trajectory of documented COVID-19 cases
&lt;i&gt;or&lt;/i&gt; a downward trajectory of positive tests as a percent of total tests (at or increasing volume of tests)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The capability to treat all patients without triggering surge capacity &lt;i&gt;and&lt;/i&gt; robust testing program in place for at-risk healthcare workers, including emerging antibody testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Florida is in the final stages of reopening, including in South Florida.  But do we meet those criteria?  Shouldn’t we be able to monitor that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-you-can-see-that-information&quot;&gt;Now you can see that information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones has used her skills to launch an &lt;mark&gt;independent dashboard using the same public data&lt;/mark&gt; that she used in the Florida Department of Health dashboard.  Her dashboard is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://experience.arcgis.com/experience/7572b118dc3c48d885d1c643c195314e/&quot;&gt;Florida’s Community Coronavirus Dashboard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-576-f806cc.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-768-f806cc.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-992-f806cc.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-1152-f806cc.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-1536-f806cc.webp 1536w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-1984-f806cc.webp 1984w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-1200-f806cc.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-2400-f806cc.webp 2400w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-576-f806cc.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-768-f806cc.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-992-f806cc.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-1152-f806cc.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-1536-f806cc.jpg 1536w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-1984-f806cc.jpg 1984w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-1200-f806cc.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-2400-f806cc.jpg 2400w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/community-coronavirus-dashboard-dade-reopening-criteria-800-f806cc.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Florida's Community Coronavirus Dashboard&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key differences is that her dashboard includes the county-by-county “report cards” for monitoring whether each county satisfies the reopening criteria.  It shows that &lt;mark&gt;many counties do not meet the State of Florida's criteria for reopening&lt;/mark&gt;.  For example, most of Florida is in Phase 2 of reopening, and Miami-Dade County is in Phase 1.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#nbcmiami:florida-governor-announces-phase-2&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;  Orange county went to Phase 2 on Friday, June 5, and theme parks have reopened.  But Jones’ dashboard includes an assessment from June 5 showing that &lt;mark&gt;Orange County does not meet the criteria&lt;/mark&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Report Card for Orange County&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Last report date: 6/5/2020&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
According to data published by the Florida Department of Health, Orange County does NOT meet the criteria for entering the next phase of reopening.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Have the following criteria decreased for a minimum of two reporting weeks?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ER Visits for Influenza-like Illness: &lt;b style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;NO&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ER Visits for COVID-like Illness: &lt;b style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;NO&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New cases by date: &lt;b style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;NO&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Information about Orange in the last one reporting week (5/30/2020-6/5/2020):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During the most recent reporting week in Orange County, ER visits for Influenza-like illness decreased by 4% and visits for COVID-like illness decreased by 35%. New cases increased by 46%.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Criteria data is measured and determined based on the trend over the last two reporting weeks, excluding the current week, summarized from Sunday-Saturday. The last report date was issued 6/5/2020. To review the state's reopening criteria, click here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Whether or not a county meets the criteria is based on the previous two-week trend, so data from the last reporting week may show a decrease in cases or ER visits but the county still may not qualify for reopening if those figures increased during the previous reporting week. Both of the two previous weeks must show a consistent downward trend, and those that increase one week or decrease the next, or for counties where there was no change, would not meet the specified criteria outlined by state.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Florida's Community Coronavirus Dashboard - Dade County Reopening Criteria&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#rebekahjones:dashboard&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Miami-Dade County &lt;mark&gt;also does not meet the reopening criteria&lt;/mark&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Report Card for Dade County&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Last report date: 6/5/2020&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
According to data published by the Florida Department of Health, Dade County does NOT meet the criteria for entering the next phase of reopening.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Have the following criteria decreased for a minimum of two reporting weeks?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ER Visits for Influenza-like Illness: &lt;b style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;NO&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ER Visits for COVID-like Illness: &lt;b style=&quot;color:green;&quot;&gt;YES&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;New cases by date: &lt;b style=&quot;color:red;&quot;&gt;NO&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Information about Dade in the last one reporting week (5/30/2020-6/5/2020):
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During the most recent reporting week in Dade County, ER visits for Influenza-like illness increased by 6% and visits for COVID-like illness decreased by 12%. New cases increased by 29%.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Criteria data is measured and determined based on the trend over the last two reporting weeks, excluding the current week, summarized from Sunday-Saturday. The last report date was issued 6/5/2020. To review the state's reopening criteria, click here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Whether or not a county meets the criteria is based on the previous two-week trend, so data from the last reporting week may show a decrease in cases or ER visits but the county still may not qualify for reopening if those figures increased during the previous reporting week. Both of the two previous weeks must show a consistent downward trend, and those that increase one week or decrease the next, or for counties where there was no change, would not meet the specified criteria outlined by state.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Florida's Community Coronavirus Dashboard - Dade County Reopening Criteria&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#rebekahjones:dashboard&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-differences&quot;&gt;Other differences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new, independent dashboard also counts coronavirus deaths differently from the official Florida dashboard.  The &lt;mark&gt;number of deaths is higher on the new dashboard&lt;/mark&gt; because it includes deaths of non-residents who were infected in Florida.  Including deaths of visitors could help to address a serious issue in tourist areas like Miami Beach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider an extreme example like the Las Vegas Strip: Very few people live on the Strip.  A significant number of &lt;mark&gt;people who will be infected in Las Vegas as it reopens will not show up in the coronavirus data&lt;/mark&gt; for Clark County, Nevada.  Their positive tests, hospitalizations, and deaths will be recorded in other places like California and Arizona instead of in Nevada.  The absence of those cases &lt;mark&gt;could lead to statistics that give a false sense of security&lt;/mark&gt; by under-reporting the impact of reopening.  Paying attention to deaths resulting from infections in Florida’s tourist areas will be important for assessing the true situation places like Miami Beach and other popular destinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;mark&gt;number of cases is also higher on the new dashboard&lt;/mark&gt; because it &lt;mark&gt;includes positive antibody tests&lt;/mark&gt;, not just positive tests for the live virus.  At least one doctor has cautioned against including these extra tests because of the false-positive rates of many of the antibody tests.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#palmbeachpost:rebekah-jones-dashboard&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The false-positive rates are a serious concern because &lt;mark&gt;the errors resulting from a test that is &quot;95% accurate&quot; can be surprisingly significant&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;including-antibody-tests-is-a-problem&quot;&gt;Including antibody tests is a problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A surprisingly low false-positive rate can have a &lt;mark&gt;significant impact on conclusions about overall infections&lt;/mark&gt; because of the base rate fallacy.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wikipedia:base-rate-fallacy&quot;&gt;[9]&lt;/a&gt;  In an example from Wikipedia:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine running an infectious disease test on a population A of 1000 people, in which &lt;mark&gt;40% are infected&lt;/mark&gt;. The test has a false positive rate of 5%, and no false negatives. 400 people would receive a true positive, and 30 people would receive a false positive.  A person receiving a positive test could be &lt;mark&gt;over 93% confident that it correctly indicates infection&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now consider the same test applied to population B, in which &lt;mark&gt;only 2% is infected&lt;/mark&gt;. 20 people would receive a true positive. 49 people would receive a false positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In population B, only 20 of the 69 total people with a positive test result are actually infected. So, the &lt;mark&gt;probability of actually being infected after testing positive is only 29%&lt;/mark&gt; for a test that otherwise appears to be “95% accurate”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The base rate for coronavirus infections is currently &lt;mark&gt;closer to the range in population B&lt;/mark&gt; than it is in population A. Please &lt;mark&gt;remember this when interpreting coronavirus data that includes antibody tests in the number of cases&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thank-you-rebekah-jones&quot;&gt;Thank you, Rebekah Jones&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The push from the governor’s office to reopen Florida counties that don’t meet the state’s reopening benchmarks is an &lt;mark&gt;obvious political problem for the governor's office&lt;/mark&gt;.  It wouldn’t be possible for the Florida Department of Health to provide a dashboard with the level of transparency that the White House Coronavirus Task Force praised if the dashboard were to show that Florida isn’t ready to reopen.  Thanks to Rebekah Jones and her independent dashboard, we now have that level of transparency again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;floridapolitics:birx-dashboard&quot;&gt;1. Downey R. &lt;b&gt;Dr. Deborah Birx highlights Florida Department of Health COVID-19 website&lt;/b&gt;. Florida Politics; 20-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://floridapolitics.com/archives/328990-dr-deborah-birx-highlights-florida-department-of-health-covid-19-website&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-06-12 09:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;floridatoday:rebekah-jones-sidelined&quot;&gt;2. Sassoon AM. &lt;b&gt;Coronavirus: As Florida re-opens, COVID-19 data chief gets sidelined and researchers cry foul&lt;/b&gt;. Florida Today; 18-May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.floridatoday.com/story/news/2020/05/18/censorship-covid-19-data-researcher-removed-florida-moves-re-open-state/5212398002/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-06-12 09:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;cbslocalmiami:jones-fired-for-public-statements&quot;&gt;3. &lt;b&gt;State Records Show Rebekah Jones Fired For Violating Health Department Policy On Public Remarks&lt;/b&gt;. CBSMiami; 24-May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://miami.cbslocal.com/2020/05/24/state-records-show-rebekah-jones-fired-violating-health-department-policy-public-remarks/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-06-12 09:45) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;rebehakjones:response-to-media&quot;&gt;4. Jones R. &lt;b&gt;Response to media: #Insubordinate #Scientists&lt;/b&gt;. Rebekah Jones; 22-May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://geojones.org/2020/05/22/public-statement/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-06-12 09:45) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;florida:plan-for-floridas-recovery&quot;&gt;5. &lt;b&gt;Plan for Florida's Recovery&lt;/b&gt;. The State of Florida; 28-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flgov.com/wp-content/uploads/covid19/Taskforce%20Report.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-06-12 10:15) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;nbcmiami:florida-governor-announces-phase-2&quot;&gt;6. &lt;b&gt;Florida Gov. Announces Phase Two of Reopening; Miami-Dade, Broward Excluded&lt;/b&gt;. NBC Miami; 3-June-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcmiami.com/news/local/gov-ron-desantis-speaking-at-universal-orlando-ahead-of-fridays-reopening-to-public/2243199/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-06-12 10:15) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;rebekahjones:dashboard&quot;&gt;7. Jones R. &lt;b&gt;Florida's Community Coronavirus Dashboard&lt;/b&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://experience.arcgis.com/experience/7572b118dc3c48d885d1c643c195314e/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;palmbeachpost:rebekah-jones-dashboard&quot;&gt;8. &lt;b&gt;Fired scientist Rebekah Jones builds coronavirus dashboard to rival Florida’s&lt;/b&gt;. The Palm Beach Post; 11-June-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.palmbeachpost.com/news/20200611/fired-scientist-rebekah-jones-builds-coronavirus-dashboard-to-rival-floridarsquos&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-06-12 10:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wikipedia:base-rate-fallacy&quot;&gt;9. &lt;b&gt;Base rate fallacy&lt;/b&gt;. Wikipedia; 4-June-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Base_rate_fallacy&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-06-12 10:45) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/06/12/censored-state-data-scientist-launches-independent-covid19-dashboard.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/06/12/censored-state-data-scientist-launches-independent-covid19-dashboard.html</guid>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Super-spreading has happened outdoors</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;We’re all watching the crowds on beaches and in Florida and elsewhere in horror.  People partying in big groups on the Lake of the Ozarks in Missouri, crowds of people floating on inner tubes on Lake Havasu in Arizona.  Crowds of people socializing shoulder-to-shoulder in Daytona and Arizona.  Walking the boardwalks in packs on the boardwalk in Ocean City, Maryland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how bad is it, really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/05/23/super-spreading-has-happened-outdoors.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/05/23/super-spreading-has-happened-outdoors.html</guid>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Estimating the cost of reaching herd immunity</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;How many people would die if we were to simply surrender to the coronavirus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When enough people have been exposed to a virus and have developed immunity,
the virus has trouble spreading because each newly-infected person is less
likely to come in contact with other vulnerable people.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#jhsph:what-is-herd-immunity&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  For example, measles, mumps, polio, and chickenpox were all common diseases in the United States.  But &lt;mark&gt;now those diseases are all rare&lt;/mark&gt; in the US, thanks to &lt;mark&gt;high levels of vaccinations&lt;/mark&gt; that have achieved herd immunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;alert alert-info float-right see-also&quot; role=&quot;alert&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h4 class=&quot;alert-heading&quot;&gt;Factoid&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The MMR vaccine for measles, mumps and rubella may offer some protection against COVID-19.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#jgold:mmr-vaccine-appears-to-confer-protection-from-covid19&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Resistance to vaccination&lt;/mark&gt; in the US has recently led to lapses in herd immunity protection from some of those diseases, which has led to &lt;mark&gt;new outbreaks of formerly-rare diseases&lt;/mark&gt;.  For example, the 2019 outbreak of measles at Disneyland in California,&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wapo:2019-measles-outbreak-at-disneyland&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-the-threshold&quot;&gt;What’s the threshold?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different viruses are different.  &lt;mark&gt;We can't stop every virus through herd immunity&lt;/mark&gt;.  It doesn’t seem to be possible with the strain of HIV that causes AIDS.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#nature:no-herd-immunity-for-HIV-1&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;  And we still don’t know enough about the SARS-CoV-2 virus that causes the COVID-19 disease to be certain that herd immunity will even stop it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a really contagious disease like measles, 90 to 93 percent of the population
needs to develop immunity to stop the spread of infection.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#whoint:herd-immunity-thresholds-for-measles&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;  Which explains why
it’s so easy for herd immunity to lapse for measles, and why it’s so easy for
new outbreaks to start when enough people reject vaccination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For SARS-CoV-2, epidemiologists think that &lt;mark&gt;about 70% to 90% of the population may need
to develop immunity&lt;/mark&gt; to have herd protection.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#jhsph:what-is-herd-immunity&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  But there is a caveat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;would-it-even-stop-at-that-point&quot;&gt;Would it even stop at that point?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herd immunity protects a population against new infections.  But if there is
already an outbreak in progress, then it &lt;mark&gt;won't immediately stop&lt;/mark&gt; when the
proportion of infected people reaches the herd immunity threshold.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#nytimes:overshoot&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;  An infection
that’s already underway will continue to spread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
A runaway train doesn’t stop when the track begins to slope uphill, and a rapidly spreading virus doesn’t stop right when herd immunity is attained.
&lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Carl T Bergstrom and Natalie Dean&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#nytimes:overshoot&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the pace of the outbreak, the COVID-19 outbreak could &lt;mark&gt;continue to spread through the United States for
months after we reach the herd immunity threshold&lt;/mark&gt;, resulting in many more
infections and many more deaths.  This concept is called “overshoot.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many more infections?  We can’t know.  It depends on too many factors, and there are too many unknowns.  But we do know that &lt;mark&gt;allowing the virus to spread uncontrolled would make the spread faster&lt;/mark&gt; and would result in going &lt;mark&gt;farther over the threshold&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#538:herd-immunity-shinyapp&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-many-people-would-die-getting-to-that-point&quot;&gt;How many people would die getting to that point?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To estimate the cost of reaching herd immunity in the United States, I’m using
the estimate that the Imperial College of London used to estimate what
would happen if the virus were to spread uncontrolled through our country.
Because &lt;mark&gt;that's what people are suggesting&lt;/mark&gt; when they propose &lt;mark&gt;surrendering to the virus&lt;/mark&gt; and trying to reach herd immunity by letting everyone get exposed.  And I’m using the estimated infection prevalence
rates for the US and Florida from their report this week.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#imperial-college:report-23-us-states&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those researchers estimated that 81% of Americans would be
infected if we were to do that.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#imperial-collect:impact-of-non-pharmaceutical-interventions&quot;&gt;[9]&lt;/a&gt;  I used that same percentage to illustrate the
&lt;mark&gt;cost in human lives&lt;/mark&gt; of reaching that point, based on the amount of death that we have already seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Dowdy, MD, PhD, infectious disease epidemiologist from Johns Hopkins University, inspired this visualization with a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidwdowdy/status/1260675514416664577&quot;&gt;powerful illustration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This resulting chart illustrates that &lt;mark&gt;millions of people in the US could die&lt;/mark&gt; if we were to surrender to the virus and allow it to spread freely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-576-f8f81d.webp 576w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-768-f8f81d.webp 768w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-992-f8f81d.webp 992w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-1152-f8f81d.webp 1152w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-1200-f8f81d.webp 1200w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-1396-f8f81d.webp 1396w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-576-f8f81d.jpg 576w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-768-f8f81d.jpg 768w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-992-f8f81d.jpg 992w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-1152-f8f81d.jpg 1152w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-1200-f8f81d.jpg 1200w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-1396-f8f81d.jpg 1396w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/united-states/2020-05-23-800-f8f81d.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Imperial College report also includes an infection prevalence estimate for
US states.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#imperial-college:report-23-us-states&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;  I used that estimate and current public data from the Florida Department of Health to provide the same visualization for the state of Florida:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-576-286670.webp 576w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-768-286670.webp 768w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-992-286670.webp 992w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-1152-286670.webp 1152w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-1200-286670.webp 1200w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-1396-286670.webp 1396w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-576-286670.jpg 576w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-768-286670.jpg 768w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-992-286670.jpg 992w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-1152-286670.jpg 1152w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-1200-286670.jpg 1200w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-1396-286670.jpg 1396w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/florida/2020-05-23-800-286670.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infection prevalence estimates are not available at the county level, but
an ongoing study that attempts to estimate the amount of
underreporting of SARS-CoV-2 infections in the United States.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#cmmid&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt;
I have been using their estimate of how many infections are reported as cases to estimate the number of infected people at the county and city levels, and those estimates have proven to be in-line with infection prevalence estimates from many different researchers. I used the same estimation method to provide visualization of the cost of reaching herd immunity for Miami-Dade and Broward Counties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-576-714ecd.webp 576w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-768-714ecd.webp 768w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-992-714ecd.webp 992w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-1152-714ecd.webp 1152w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-1200-714ecd.webp 1200w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-1396-714ecd.webp 1396w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-576-714ecd.jpg 576w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-768-714ecd.jpg 768w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-992-714ecd.jpg 992w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-1152-714ecd.jpg 1152w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-1200-714ecd.jpg 1200w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-1396-714ecd.jpg 1396w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/miami-dade/2020-05-23-800-714ecd.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-576-c79cfc.webp 576w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-768-c79cfc.webp 768w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-992-c79cfc.webp 992w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-1152-c79cfc.webp 1152w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-1200-c79cfc.webp 1200w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-1396-c79cfc.webp 1396w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-576-c79cfc.jpg 576w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-768-c79cfc.jpg 768w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-992-c79cfc.jpg 992w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-1152-c79cfc.jpg 1152w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-1200-c79cfc.jpg 1200w, /generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-1396-c79cfc.jpg 1396w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/charts/the-cost-of-herd-immunity/broward/2020-05-23-800-c79cfc.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;okay-so-what-does-this-mean&quot;&gt;Okay, so what does this mean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intentionally &lt;mark&gt;aiming at herd immunity is not the answer&lt;/mark&gt;.  If we allow the virus to spread uncontrolled, or if we go so far as to encourage the spread, then the outbreak will rocket past the herd immunity threshold, and people will continue to be infected.  And we will have more deaths for months after we reach that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;We &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;must&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; reduce the final death count.&lt;/mark&gt;  The only way to do that is by &lt;mark&gt;lowering the fatality rate&lt;/mark&gt; through new therapies, or by &lt;mark&gt;stopping the spread with a vaccine&lt;/mark&gt;.  We must buy time for those things by limiting the spread now.  The biggest factor that affects the spread is under our control: social distancing.  Weather, overall health, and other things are all factors, but social distancing dwarfs those factors.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#policylab:forecasting-impacts-of-weather&quot;&gt;[11,12]&lt;/a&gt;  We’re at a point right now where we risk a second outbreak that we might not be able to control, and the best way that we have to stop it is to maintain social distancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the challenge of our lifetime.  &lt;mark&gt;We can't simply surrender to the virus.  Too many people who we love and who we need would die.&lt;/mark&gt;  We must do this.  I’m aiming my visualizations here at reminding us &lt;mark&gt;what we're fighting for&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-then-what-is-the-answer&quot;&gt;So then what &lt;i&gt;IS&lt;/i&gt; the answer?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no way to avoid an enormous cost from this.  &lt;mark&gt;The only control that we have is over &lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;where&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt; the cost is.&lt;/mark&gt;  We can either&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Surrender to the virus, and the cost will be hundreds of millions of human lives worldwide,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shut down forever, and the cost will be the irreparable destruction of the global economy, and mass suffering from that, or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobilize and invest in testing and tracing and isolating so that we can quarantine the correct people instead of quarantining everyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you choose not to decide, &lt;mark&gt;you still have made a choice&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#rush:free-will&quot;&gt;[13]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-community&quot;&gt;Your community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re reading this from somewhere outside of South Florida, and you’re
interested in seeing &lt;mark&gt;what the cost of reaching herd immunity might look like for your community&lt;/mark&gt;, please take a look at the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/endymion/BeachAnalytics/raw/master/analysis/The%20cost%20of%20reaching%20herd%20immunity.xlsx&quot;&gt;Excel file&lt;/a&gt; that I used to generate these charts.  I designed it so that it’s easy for you to plug in data for your area.  You’ll need a population count, and if you want to go
more fine-grained than the state level, then you’ll currently need to use a
confirmed case count to estimate your true infection prevalence in your area.
Please be sure to check the latest underreporting estimate from the Center
for Mathematical Modeling of Infectious Diseases at the London School of Hygiene
and Tropical Medicine&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#cmmid&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt;, because they update their estimates frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jhsph:what-is-herd-immunity&quot;&gt;1. &lt;b&gt;What is Herd Immunity and How Can We Achieve It With COVID-19?&lt;/b&gt; Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health; 19-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jhsph.edu/covid-19/articles/achieving-herd-immunity-with-covid19.html&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-23 12:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jgold:mmr-vaccine-appears-to-confer-protection-from-covid19&quot;&gt;2. Gold JE. &lt;b&gt;MMR Vaccine Appears to Confer Strong Protection from COVID-19: Few Deaths from SARS-CoV-2 in Highly Vaccinated Populations&lt;/b&gt;. ResearchGate; May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/341354165_MMR_Vaccine_Appears_to_Confer_Strong_Protection_from_COVID-19_Few_Deaths_from_SARS-CoV-2_in_Highly_Vaccinated_Populations&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-23 18:20) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wapo:2019-measles-outbreak-at-disneyland&quot;&gt;3. &lt;b&gt;A tourist infected with measles visited Disneyland and other Southern California hot spots in mid-August&lt;/b&gt;. The Washington Post; 24-August-2019 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2019/08/24/tourist-infected-with-measles-visited-disneyland-other-southern-california-hotspots-mid-august/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-23 18:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;nature:no-herd-immunity-for-HIV-1&quot;&gt;4. &lt;b&gt;Pandemic HIV-1 Vpu overcomes intrinsic herd immunity mediated by tetherin&lt;/b&gt;. Springer Nature Limited; 17-July-2015 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/srep12256&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-23 18:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;whoint:herd-immunity-thresholds-for-measles&quot;&gt;5. Funk S. &lt;b&gt;Critical immunity thresholds  for measles elimination&lt;/b&gt;. Centre for the Mathematical Modelling of Infectious Diseases London School of Hygiene &amp;amp; Tropical Medicine; 9-October-2017 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/immunization/sage/meetings/2017/october/2._target_immunity_levels_FUNK.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-23 18:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;nytimes:overshoot&quot;&gt;6. Bergstrom CT, Dean N. &lt;b&gt;What the Proponents of ‘Natural’ Herd Immunity Don’t Say&lt;/b&gt;. The New York Times; 1-May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/01/opinion/sunday/coronavirus-herd-immunity.html&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-23 18:40) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;538:herd-immunity-shinyapp&quot;&gt;7. Rogers K, Wolfe J, Bronner L. &lt;b&gt;Without A Vaccine, Herd Immunity Won’t Save Us&lt;/b&gt;. 538; 13-May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/without-a-vaccine-herd-immunity-wont-save-us/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-23 22:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-college:report-23-us-states&quot;&gt;8. Unwin HJT, Mishra∗2 S, Bradley VC, et al. &lt;b&gt;Report 23: State-level tracking of COVID-19 in the United States&lt;/b&gt;. Imperial College COVID-19 Response Team; 21-May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-23-united-states/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;; DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.25561/79231&quot;&gt;10.25561/79231&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-collect:impact-of-non-pharmaceutical-interventions&quot;&gt;9. &lt;b&gt;Report 9: Impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) to reduce COVID-19 mortality and healthcare demand&lt;/b&gt;. Imperial College London - MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis; 16-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/sph/ide/gida-fellowships/Imperial-College-COVID19-NPI-modelling-16-03-2020.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;; DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.25561/77735&quot;&gt;10.25561/77735&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;cmmid&quot;&gt;10. Russell TW, Hellewell J, Abbott S, et al. &lt;b&gt;Using a delay-adjusted case fatality ratio to estimate under-reporting&lt;/b&gt;. Centre for the Mathematical Modelling of Infectious Diseases at the London School of Hygiene &amp;amp; Tropical Medicine; 17-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmmid.github.io/topics/covid19/global_cfr_estimates.html&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-17 19:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;policylab:forecasting-impacts-of-weather&quot;&gt;11. &lt;b&gt;Forecasting the Impacts of Weather and Social Distancing on COVID-19 Transmission Across the U.S.&lt;/b&gt; PolicyLab at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia Research Institute; &lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/project/forecasting-impacts-weather-and-social-distancing-covid-19-transmission-across-us&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 15:20) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;policylab:studying-effect-of-weather&quot;&gt;12. &lt;b&gt;PolicyLab Studying Effect of Weather, Social Distancing on Local COVID-19 Spread&lt;/b&gt;. PolicyLab at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia Research Institute; 21-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/blog/policylab-studying-effect-weather-social-distancing-local-covid-19-spread&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 15:15) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;rush:free-will&quot;&gt;13. Peart N. &lt;b&gt;Free Will&lt;/b&gt;. Mercury Records; 14-January-1980 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rush.com/songs/freewill/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/05/23/estimating-the-cost-of-reaching-herd-immunity.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/05/23/estimating-the-cost-of-reaching-herd-immunity.html</guid>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>South Florida may see a new outbreak soon</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Epidemiologists widely agree that reducing social distancing while we still have active community transmission will lead to an increase in cases, and possibly an uncontrollable outbreak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already know that cellphone data shows that &lt;mark&gt;South Florida has &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/05/16/south-florida-gives-up-on-social-distancing.html&quot;&gt;not been&lt;/a&gt; engaging in social distancing&lt;/mark&gt; as well as we were during the start of the first wave of our coronavirus epidemic.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-miami-dade&quot;&gt;[1,2,3]&lt;/a&gt;  But what does that mean for us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;alert alert-info float-right see-also&quot; role=&quot;alert&quot;&gt;
  &lt;h4 class=&quot;alert-heading&quot;&gt;See also&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/05/16/south-florida-gives-up-on-social-distancing.html&quot;&gt;South Florida gives up on social distancing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data analysis shows a clear pattern: &lt;mark&gt;States that have successfully limited the spread have practiced social distancing more aggressively&lt;/mark&gt;, and even more so when their death rate started to rise.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ut:mortality-modeling-faq&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;  But there aren’t a lot of epidemiologists tailoring advice to South Florida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What do the forecast models say?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the computer models &lt;mark&gt;can't tell us much about what might happen in South Florida&lt;/mark&gt;, specifically.  Their designers didn’t build them for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the models can’t help us to forecast our future in South Florida because they have a &lt;mark&gt;coarse granularity&lt;/mark&gt;, only issuing projections at the state level.  Our situation in South Florida is very different from a lot of the rest of the state of Florida, and we need forecasts that can see the difference between a dense, urban area like Miami or Miami Beach, versus rural communities like Dixie County or Highlands County.  Researchers have found that &lt;mark&gt;the risk of infection and death is different in crowded areas like South Florida&lt;/mark&gt;, versus rural areas.  Large, densely-populated areas like New York and Chicago had nearly &lt;mark&gt;twice the rate of transmission&lt;/mark&gt; in the first two weeks of their outbreaks than less densely-populated areas like Birmingham, Alabama, or the metro area of Portland, Oregon.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#nytimes:crowding-affects-the-spread&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some models, like the University of Texas and IHME models, do account for changes in social distancing, but they &lt;mark&gt;update their assumptions about social distancing levels infrequently&lt;/mark&gt;, and they &lt;mark&gt;assume that levels will remain constant&lt;/mark&gt; until the next update.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ut:mortality-modeling-faq&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ihme:forecasting-the-impact-of-the-first-wave&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;  Researchers at the University of Texas provide this caveat&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ut:mortality-modeling-faq&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; for their forecasts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
Our model explicitly assumes that social distancing behavior remains at the levels we've observed over the last seven days of data. If that doesn't happen, you can &lt;mark&gt;throw our model's projections out the window beyond about ten days in the future&lt;/mark&gt;.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers behind most of the models only designed their forecasts to project &lt;mark&gt;one wave of our epidemic&lt;/mark&gt;.  They generally assume that social distancing will remain constant, or they only update their estimates of social distancing levels periodically. Accuracy analysis seems to show that these models &lt;mark&gt;can be effective at forecasting a single peak&lt;/mark&gt; in the death rate that has been mitigated by social distancing. But they can’t account for multiple peaks in the death rate caused by separate waves of COVID-19 transmission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Forecasting COVID-19 in South Florida&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experts in public health at PolicyLab at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia Research Institute have provided a &lt;mark&gt;different kind of model&lt;/mark&gt;.  Theirs is the only publicly-available model that &lt;mark&gt;projects the risk of a new outbreak in small geographic areas&lt;/mark&gt; through the summer as we begin to reopen now, while accounting for other changing factors such as weather.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#policylab:new-model&quot;&gt;[7,8,9]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
 As our leaders plan for when and how to reopen communities, understanding the highly contagious nature of this virus and the factors that impact its spread must inform those decisions.  Complementary to other national models, our data differ in that they illustrate the situation in our own backyards. With our model, we hope to help city leaders and public health officials build more targeted strategies for reopening communities that consider not only the strain on our health care systems, but also how to deploy other strategies such as masking and workplace safety regulations to maintain some distancing as people leave the confines of their homes.
 &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Dr. David Rubin, director of PolicyLab and a professor of Pediatrics at the University of Pennsylvania’s Perelman School of Medicine&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#policylab:new-model&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;alert alert-info float-right see-also&quot; role=&quot;alert&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;mb-0&quot;&gt;&lt;i class=&quot;fa fa-info-circle&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; PolicyLab researchers found that warming spring temperatures are helping to reduce the spread of SARS-CoV-2 infections in some areas, but that effect is dwarfed by the impact of population density.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PolicyLab model, known as COVID-Lab: Mapping COVID-19 in Your Community looks at how population factors like &lt;mark&gt;age, insurance status, and smoking prevalence&lt;/mark&gt; have affected the number and spread of coronavirus cases across a county.  Their model also looks at city characteristics like density.  It uses the &lt;mark&gt;same cellphone mobility data from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unacast.com&quot;&gt;Unacast&lt;/a&gt; that showed us recently that South Florida has started to give up on social distancing&lt;/mark&gt;,&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#unacast:methodology&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt; and it has identified &lt;mark&gt;social distancing as the most important factor&lt;/mark&gt; in reducing transmission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
Measured against a number of local factors, we saw that strict social distancing policies and low population density, and, to a lesser extent, warming weather were all important in slowing the spread of this dangerous virus.  We were especially interested to find that rising temperatures may have helped reduce the spread of COVID-19, particularly in our less populous counties, but unfortunately the effect of weather, in the absence of strict social distancing policies, has not been strong enough to prevent resurgent transmission in our most crowded cities and their metropolitan areas.
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Dr. Gregory Tasian, faculty member at PolicyLab, assistant professor of Urology and Epidemiology and senior scholar in the Center for Clinical Epidemiology and Biostatistics at the University of Pennsylvania’s Perelman School of Medicine&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#policylab:new-model&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Projections for Miami-Dade and Broward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the projections from the PolicyLab model don’t look good for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-576-5aacd3.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-768-5aacd3.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-992-5aacd3.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1152-5aacd3.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1200-5aacd3.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1406-5aacd3.webp 1406w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-576-5aacd3.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-768-5aacd3.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-992-5aacd3.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1152-5aacd3.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1200-5aacd3.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1406-5aacd3.jpg 1406w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-800-5aacd3.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Miami-Dade County - Projected cases for four weeks.&lt;br /&gt;credit:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/covid-lab-mapping-covid-19-your-community&quot;&gt;PolicyLab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-576-0983db.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-768-0983db.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-992-0983db.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1152-0983db.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1200-0983db.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1406-0983db.webp 1406w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-576-0983db.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-768-0983db.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-992-0983db.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1152-0983db.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1200-0983db.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-1406-0983db.jpg 1406w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Broward--Projected-cases-for-four-weeks--PolicyLab-800-0983db.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Broward County - Projected cases for four weeks.&lt;br /&gt;credit:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/covid-lab-mapping-covid-19-your-community&quot;&gt;PolicyLab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model estimates that &lt;mark&gt;each person infected with SARS-CoV-2 in Miami-Dade County might already be infecting more than one person&lt;/mark&gt;, on average.  The infection will &lt;mark&gt;begin to spread exponentially again&lt;/mark&gt; if this metric goes above 1.0 for an extended period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-576-a44025.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-768-a44025.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-992-a44025.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1152-a44025.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1200-a44025.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1406-a44025.webp 1406w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-576-a44025.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-768-a44025.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-992-a44025.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1152-a44025.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1200-a44025.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1406-a44025.jpg 1406w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Miami-Dade--R-estimate--PolicyLab-800-a44025.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Miami-Dade County - Estimated R, a metric representing the rate of spread.&lt;br /&gt;credit:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/covid-lab-mapping-covid-19-your-community&quot;&gt;PolicyLab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-576-7ac6f5.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-768-7ac6f5.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-992-7ac6f5.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1152-7ac6f5.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1200-7ac6f5.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1406-7ac6f5.webp 1406w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-576-7ac6f5.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-768-7ac6f5.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-992-7ac6f5.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1152-7ac6f5.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1200-7ac6f5.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-1406-7ac6f5.jpg 1406w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/Broward--R-estimate--PolicyLab-800-7ac6f5.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Miami-Dade County - Estimated R, a metric representing the rate of spread.&lt;br /&gt;credit:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/covid-lab-mapping-covid-19-your-community&quot;&gt;PolicyLab&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Another model echoes the same warning for Florida&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Imperial College COVID-19 Response Team is using a &lt;mark&gt;similar statistical
model&lt;/mark&gt; that projects the impact of increases in mobility.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#imperial-college:report-23-us-states&quot;&gt;[11]&lt;/a&gt;  Their model does not
address the potential impact of changes in behavior.  Like mask-wearing and
attempts at social distancing in public settings like restaurants and beaches.
Their model doesn’t reach the county-level granularity that the PolicyLab model
does, but it &lt;mark&gt;reinforces the PolicyLab suggestion that the outbreak is not
under control in Florida&lt;/mark&gt;.  And that changes in mobility could lead to an
&lt;mark&gt;exponential growth in infections and deaths&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their model avoids &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/04/29/dont-focus-on-the-center-line.html&quot;&gt;conveying false precision&lt;/a&gt; by preventing results as a range of confidence instead of a single center line like the PolicyLab model.  They give projections based on three different scenarios:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobility stays constant, which was can clearly see is not the scenario that’s happening.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobility increases by 20%.  We know from other data that this has &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/05/16/south-florida-gives-up-on-social-distancing.html&quot;&gt;already happened&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mobility increasing by 40%.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their &lt;a href=&quot;https://mrc-ide.github.io/covid19usa/#/details/FL&quot;&gt;dashboard for Florida&lt;/a&gt; for their model output shows a few disturbing
charts, including this one for projected deaths:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-576-d63575.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-768-d63575.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-992-d63575.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-1152-d63575.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-1200-d63575.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-1332-d63575.webp 1332w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-576-d63575.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-768-d63575.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-992-d63575.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-1152-d63575.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-1200-d63575.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-1332-d63575.jpg 1332w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/imperial-college-london-covid19-model-florida-deaths-2020-05-17-800-d63575.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Florida - Projected number of deaths - May 17, 2020&lt;br /&gt;credit:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mrc-ide.github.io/covid19usa/#/details/FL&quot;&gt;Imperial College COVID-19 Response Team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Imperial College model also doesn’t account for Memorial Day weekend crowds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What does this mean for us here?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Rubin and Paul A. Offit from PolicyLab advise that rural areas that are less densely populated or that are already benefiting from warmer spring temperatures will probably be able to reopen more quickly, as long as the number of cases in their area has sharply reduced.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#nytimes:crowding-affects-the-spread&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they say that large, &lt;mark&gt;densely populated cities like Miami need a more cautious plan&lt;/mark&gt;.  For two reasons: &lt;mark&gt;More crowded areas increase the risk of spread&lt;/mark&gt;.  And also because we’re learning that &lt;mark&gt;crowding itself may also affect the death rate&lt;/mark&gt;. You could get sicker and have a &lt;mark&gt;higher risk of dying if you're exposed to more of the virus&lt;/mark&gt; because you’re in a densely-populated area. That’s also what seems to have happened during the 1918 Influenza pandemic.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#plosone:influenza-dose-may-explain-high-mortailty-in-subsequent-waves&quot;&gt;[12]&lt;/a&gt;  One of the first studies of a documented super-spreading event from carnival festivities in Germany also showed that people who were infected in dense crowds ended up sicker than those who were infected in other scenarios.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#streeck:ifr-from-superspreading-at-carnival-in-germany&quot;&gt;[13]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
We found a &lt;mark&gt;highly significant increase in both infection rate and number of symptoms&lt;/mark&gt; when people attended carnival festivities, as compared to people who did not celebrate carnival.
  &lt;footer class=&quot;blockquote-footer&quot;&gt;Hendrik Streeck et al, University Hospital of Bonn, Germany&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#streeck:ifr-from-superspreading-at-carnival-in-germany&quot;&gt;[13]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest factors in the PolicyLab projections is social distancing,
and their model assumes that social distancing levels will remain constant in
the future.(missing reference)  So, if social distancing
levels continue to decrease as South Florida reopens then updates of the model
could look even worse for us here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In South Florida, we should remember as we make decisions about reopening that nation-wide and state-wide trends and forecasts don’t necessarily apply directly to us.  Because they include a lot of areas where we know that the rate of the spread and the death rate will probably be significantly lower than we will experience here. The only forecast model currently available that’s aimed at helping us with those decisions for our local community is warning that we may soon see a new outbreak that may be impossible to control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-miami-dade&quot;&gt;1. &lt;b&gt;Social Distancing Scoreboard - Miami-Dade County&lt;/b&gt;. Unacast; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unacast.com/covid19/social-distancing-scoreboard?view=county&amp;amp;fips=12086&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-16 21:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;safegraph:us-geographic-responsed-to-shelter-in-place-orders&quot;&gt;2. &lt;b&gt;U.S. Geographic Responses to Shelter in Place Orders&lt;/b&gt;. SafeGraph; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.safegraph.com/dashboard/covid19-shelter-in-place?s=FL&amp;amp;d=05-17-2020&amp;amp;t=counties&amp;amp;m=index&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 14:20) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;descartes-lab:changes-in-us-mobility&quot;&gt;3. &lt;b&gt;Coronavirus: Changes in US Mobility&lt;/b&gt;. Descartes Labs; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.descarteslabs.com/mobility/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 21:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ut:mortality-modeling-faq&quot;&gt;4. &lt;b&gt;Mortality Modeling FAQ&lt;/b&gt;. The University of Texas at Austin COVID-19 Modeling Consortium; &lt;a href=&quot;https://covid-19.tacc.utexas.edu/mortality-projection-faq/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 14:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;nytimes:crowding-affects-the-spread&quot;&gt;5. &lt;b&gt;We Know Crowding Affects the Spread. It May Affect the Death Rate.&lt;/b&gt; The New York Times; 27-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/04/27/opinion/coronavirus-crowds.html&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 15:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ihme:forecasting-the-impact-of-the-first-wave&quot;&gt;6. &lt;b&gt;Forecasting the impact of the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic on hospital demand and deaths for the USA and European Economic Area countries&lt;/b&gt;. IHME COVID-19 health service utilization forecasting team; 21-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healthdata.org/sites/default/files/files/Projects/COVID/RA_COVID-forecasting-USA-EEA_042120.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-27 16:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;policylab:new-model&quot;&gt;7. &lt;b&gt;New Model Shows Competing Influences of Social Distancing, Population Density &amp;amp; Temperature on Local COVID-19 Transmission&lt;/b&gt;. PolicyLab at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia Research Institute; 22-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/press-releases/new-model-shows-competing-influences-social-distancing-population-density-temperature&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 15:10) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;policylab:studying-effect-of-weather&quot;&gt;8. &lt;b&gt;PolicyLab Studying Effect of Weather, Social Distancing on Local COVID-19 Spread&lt;/b&gt;. PolicyLab at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia Research Institute; 21-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/blog/policylab-studying-effect-weather-social-distancing-local-covid-19-spread&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 15:15) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;policylab:forecasting-impacts-of-weather&quot;&gt;9. &lt;b&gt;Forecasting the Impacts of Weather and Social Distancing on COVID-19 Transmission Across the U.S.&lt;/b&gt; PolicyLab at the Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia Research Institute; &lt;a href=&quot;https://policylab.chop.edu/project/forecasting-impacts-weather-and-social-distancing-covid-19-transmission-across-us&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 15:20) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;unacast:methodology&quot;&gt;10. Walle T. &lt;b&gt;The Unacast Social Distancing Scoreboard - Methodology&lt;/b&gt;. Unacast; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unacast.com/post/the-unacast-social-distancing-scoreboard&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-16 21:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-college:report-23-us-states&quot;&gt;11. Unwin HJT, Mishra∗2 S, Bradley VC, et al. &lt;b&gt;Report 23: State-level tracking of COVID-19 in the United States&lt;/b&gt;. Imperial College COVID-19 Response Team; 21-May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/mrc-global-infectious-disease-analysis/covid-19/report-23-united-states/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;; DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.25561/79231&quot;&gt;10.25561/79231&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;plosone:influenza-dose-may-explain-high-mortailty-in-subsequent-waves&quot;&gt;12. &lt;b&gt;Influenza Infectious Dose May Explain the High Mortality of the Second and Third Wave of 1918–1919 Influenza Pandemic&lt;/b&gt;. PLoS One; &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article/file?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0011655&amp;amp;type=printable&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-21 15:20) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;streeck:ifr-from-superspreading-at-carnival-in-germany&quot;&gt;13. &lt;b&gt;Infection fatality rate of SARS-CoV-2 infection in a German community with a super-spreading event&lt;/b&gt;. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press; 18-May-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.05.04.20090076v1&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;; DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.05.04.20090076&quot;&gt;10.1101/2020.05.04.20090076&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/05/21/South-Florida-may-see-a-new-outbreak-soon.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/05/21/South-Florida-may-see-a-new-outbreak-soon.html</guid>
            
            <category>covid19-models</category>
            
            <category>mobility-data</category>
            
            <category>unacast</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>South Florida gives up on social distancing</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Miami-Dade County started to give up on social distancing even before it started reopening.  And South Florida currently has one of the lowest success rates of any area in the United States in terms of social distancing, according to a company that’s analyzing location data to determine how many contacts each person has.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-you-measure-social-distancing&quot;&gt;How do you measure social distancing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of April, residents of Miami-Dade County were moving around a lot less than before the coronavirus pandemic, based on data from cellphones.  A company called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unacast.com&quot;&gt;Unacast&lt;/a&gt;, a spinoff of the Tidal music service, collects location data from app partners and uses it to analyze people’s movements.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#unacast:methodology&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  Their data shows Miami-Dade residents moving around 55% to 70% less than in February.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-miami-dade&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even before we started to ease our restrictions, data shows that Miami-Dade residents have increased their mobility.  Now their data shows people climbing to only about 45% less than February levels.  A significant increase from the approximately 70% reduction in mobility that we saw in early April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-many-people-have-you-seen&quot;&gt;How many people have you seen?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Measuring how far people are traveling is one indication of social distancing.  But you can drive a long way and then come back home without ever getting near anyone.  Or you could walk a few hundred feet and find yourself in a crowd of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unacast also measures how many people the average person is coming within prolonged contact.  And unfortunately, South Floridians are not very good at keeping to themselves.  According to Unacast’s data, Miami-Dade and Broward rank among the worst places in the US at achieving social distancing.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-miami-dade&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-broward&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;  Both counties currently show a D+ grade on the Unacast Social Distancing Scoreboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-did-this-happen&quot;&gt;When did this happen?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most-social moment that Miami-Dade has seen since the start of the shutdown was last weekend, on Saturday, May 9, when the average person in Miami-Dade came in contact with seven and a half times as many other people as the national baseline.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-miami-dade&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;  In Broward County, the average person came in contact with even more people, more than eight times the national baseline.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-broward&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can only expect to see social distancing behavior decrease even more as South Florida begins its phased reopening.  Epidemiologists are nearly unanimous in warning that these increased social contacts will lead to more infections and more death.  Dr. Anthony Fauci and other public health experts have explicitly warned that this will “likely” lead to a second wave of the COVID-19 epidemic&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#cnbc:likelihood-that-we-will-have-a-rebound&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; that epidemiologists warn could be largely uncontrolled.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#oxford:overshoot&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;unacast:methodology&quot;&gt;1. Walle T. &lt;b&gt;The Unacast Social Distancing Scoreboard - Methodology&lt;/b&gt;. Unacast; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unacast.com/post/the-unacast-social-distancing-scoreboard&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-16 21:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-miami-dade&quot;&gt;2. &lt;b&gt;Social Distancing Scoreboard - Miami-Dade County&lt;/b&gt;. Unacast; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unacast.com/covid19/social-distancing-scoreboard?view=county&amp;amp;fips=12086&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-16 21:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;unacast:social-distancing-scoreboard-broward&quot;&gt;3. &lt;b&gt;Social Distancing Scoreboard - Broward County&lt;/b&gt;. Unacast; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.unacast.com/covid19/social-distancing-scoreboard?view=county&amp;amp;fips=12011&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-05-16 21:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;cnbc:likelihood-that-we-will-have-a-rebound&quot;&gt;4. Higgins-Dunn N, Kolodny L. &lt;b&gt;Trump says he ‘totally disagrees’ with Georgia Gov. Kemp’s decision to reopen businesses in the middle of coronavirus pandemic&lt;/b&gt;. CNBC; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/04/22/trump-says-he-totally-disagrees-with-georgia-gov-kemps-decision-to-reopen-businesses-in-the-middle-of-coronavirus-pandemic.html&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;oxford:overshoot&quot;&gt;5. Tanaka MM, Althouse BM, Bergstrom CT. &lt;b&gt;Timing of antimicrobial use influences the evolution of antimicrobial resistance during disease epidemics&lt;/b&gt;. Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health; &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/emph/article/2014/1/150/1846924&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/05/16/south-florida-gives-up-on-social-distancing.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/05/16/south-florida-gives-up-on-social-distancing.html</guid>
            
            <category>mobility-data</category>
            
            <category>unacast</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Don't focus on the center line</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Don’t treat the center line of the IHME forecast charts as a precise prediction, any more than you would assume that a hurricane will follow the center line on the NHC hurricane forecast cone images.  The forecast is a wide range, not a specific number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people are misinterpreting the COVID-19 &lt;a href=&quot;/ihme-model.html&quot;&gt;forecast model&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Washington’s Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation.  In Florida, we already have some experience with one of the ways that people are misinterpreting the forecasts from our &lt;mark&gt;experience interpreting hurricane forecasts&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-a-range-not-a-precise-prediction&quot;&gt;It’s a range, not a precise prediction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the morning of Friday, 13 August 2004 during Hurricane Charley, the National Hurricane Center’s forecast for the path of the hurricane showed a &lt;mark&gt;cone of uncertainty&lt;/mark&gt; for where the storm would make landfall that &lt;mark&gt;showed the center line of the storm passing directly over Tampa Bay&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1100.gif&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1100-576-0f407c.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1100-768-0f407c.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1100-895-0f407c.webp 895w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1100-576-0f407c.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1100-768-0f407c.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1100-895-0f407c.jpg 895w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1100-800-0f407c.gif&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;The center line of the 11 AM forecast showed Hurricane Charley striking Tampa Bay.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the &lt;mark&gt;forecast changed&lt;/mark&gt; that afternoon, shifting the center line to Charlotte County, &lt;mark&gt;a hundred miles south&lt;/mark&gt; of Tampa.  That area, full of retirees, was devastated when the hurricane struck Punta Gorda in Charlotte County.  People hadn’t evacuated because they &lt;mark&gt;thought that the NHC was telling them that the storm was going to hit Tampa Bay&lt;/mark&gt;, a hundred miles north of them.&lt;mark&gt;  Misinterpretation of a forecast graphic cost lives.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1500.gif&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1500-576-121975.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1500-768-121975.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1500-895-121975.webp 895w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1500-576-121975.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1500-768-121975.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1500-895-121975.jpg 895w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/NHC-Hurricane-Charley-2004-08-13-1500-800-121975.gif&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;The center line of the 2 PM forecast shifted a hundred miles southward.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meteorologists at the National Hurricane Center are so concerned that people will pay too much attention to the center line of the hurricane track forecast cone images&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#bams:cone-of-uncertainty&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; that they have &lt;mark&gt;removed the center line&lt;/mark&gt; from the default forecast images.  They do still publish a set of forecast images with center lines, but the default images no longer include the misleading center track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/nhc-hurricane-cone.png&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/nhc-hurricane-cone-576-ce9097.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/nhc-hurricane-cone-768-ce9097.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/nhc-hurricane-cone-960-ce9097.webp 960w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/nhc-hurricane-cone-576-ce9097.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/nhc-hurricane-cone-768-ce9097.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/nhc-hurricane-cone-960-ce9097.jpg 960w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/nhc-hurricane-cone-800-ce9097.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;The default hurricane forecast images from the National Hurricane Center no longer include a misleading center-line forecast track.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;same-problem-with-covid-19-projections&quot;&gt;Same problem with COVID-19 projections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easy-to-understand center line in the IHME charts comes with the &lt;mark&gt;exact same problem&lt;/mark&gt;.  Many people, including even President Trump, have misinterpreted the center line of the IHME projections.  Trump’s famously-optimistic projection that only 60,000 people would die in the entire COVID-19 epidemic in the US was an obvious misinterpretation of both the center line of the IHME charts and the overall intent of the model: to project the impact of the &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/04/27/its-not-the-peak-its-this-peak.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;first wave&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of the epidemic.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wapo:misunderstanding-the-math&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/ihme-forecast-range.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/ihme-forecast-range-576-8174c9.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/ihme-forecast-range-768-8174c9.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/ihme-forecast-range-783-8174c9.webp 783w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/ihme-forecast-range-576-8174c9.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/ihme-forecast-range-768-8174c9.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/ihme-forecast-range-783-8174c9.jpg 783w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/ihme-forecast-range-783-8174c9.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;A confusing center line on a forecast that's really a range from about 57k to about 130k.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the center line on the charts leads people to treat the model like a crystal ball that will give them a specific answer.  And then when the real death count doesn’t track the center line exactly, they’re &lt;mark&gt;disillusioned and they reject the whole model&lt;/mark&gt;.  Or when researchers update the parameters of the model and the forecast line changes.  This stems from a tragic misunderstanding of what the model is trying to forecast and now it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the worst case, people will misinterpret the IHME model’s reports as saying that the threat of COVID-19 is over and that it’s okay to stop the social distancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-a-crystal-ball&quot;&gt;Not a crystal ball&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The readout on the dashboard of the IHME model forecasts the deaths precisely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
74,073 COVID-19 deaths
projected by August 4, 2020
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ihme:covid19&quot;&gt;Ferguson PN, Bhatt DS. &lt;b&gt;COVID-19 Projections&lt;/b&gt;. Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation, University of Washington; 27-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://covid19.healthdata.org/united-states-of-america&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-29 09:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the way down to seventy-three?  Really?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No.  The actual forecast, as of this writing, is a &lt;mark&gt;wide range&lt;/mark&gt;.  From about 57,000 deaths by August 4 to about 130,000 deaths, or anywhere in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;misleading-journalism&quot;&gt;Misleading journalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s especially dangerous when journalists misunderstand the IHME results and report on them, because they &lt;mark&gt;inadvertently spread risky misinformation&lt;/mark&gt;.  In one recent example, CNN reported that “Last week, the model projected 67,641 deaths from Covid-19.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of &lt;mark&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_precision&quot;&gt;false precision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/mark&gt;, when numerical data is presented in a manner that implies better precision than is justified.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wikipedia:false_precision&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;  Stating the forecast in terms of &lt;mark&gt;a precise center line confuses readers&lt;/mark&gt;.  Such an exact projection is obviously ridiculous, and people who spread misinformation have used that to &lt;mark&gt;ridicule the overly-precise IHME forecasts&lt;/mark&gt; and advance a narrative that the experts have been completely wrong about the virus.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#infowars:virologists-question-lockdowns&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;  When the real numbers don’t track the forecast precisely, people then misinterpret or misrepresent the error as evidence that the entire model is invalid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t blame CNN too much in this case, because the false precision comes directly from the IHME dashboard.  The charts on the dashboard clearly show a forecast &lt;em&gt;range&lt;/em&gt;, but they also give a handy total.  Currently “74,073 COVID-19 deaths”.  The number of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Significant_figures&quot;&gt;significant figures&lt;/a&gt; in the dashboard’s own totals are &lt;mark&gt;inappropriately overstating the precision of the forecast&lt;/mark&gt;,&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wikipedia:significant_figures&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; and are &lt;mark&gt;misleading to the public&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Journalists should cite the full range of the forecast&lt;/mark&gt; and the caveat that the model is only forecasting one wave.  For example: “The IHME model currently forecasts the total death rate in the US from the first wave of the COVID-19 outbreak will fall in the range from about 22 thousand people to about 122 thousand people.”  &lt;mark&gt;Journalists should not overstate the precision of the forecast by reporting the center line&lt;/mark&gt; of the projections or by using too many significant figures.  And the &lt;mark&gt;models themselves should avoid portraying false precision&lt;/mark&gt; by stating broad ranges instead of the center-line forecast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;another-big-misconception&quot;&gt;Another big misconception&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another popular misconception about the IHME forecasts is the idea that the model predicts a single wave, possibly in part because the model’s charts all show a single hump that peaks and then subsides.  That isn’t what the model is forecasting, but you have to understand how the model works to understand that the charts showing the infection dropping to zero and then staying at zero are not really forecasting that the infection will do that.  The model is &lt;mark&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/04/27/its-not-the-peak-its-this-peak.html&quot;&gt;only forecasting&lt;/a&gt; the impact of the first wave&lt;/mark&gt;.  &lt;mark&gt;The phrase &quot;by August 4&quot; is important!&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IHME’s COVID-19 forecasting model dashboard overstates the precision of the model’s projections.  This does a &lt;mark&gt;disservice to planners and to the public&lt;/mark&gt; by encouraging them to look at the model as a crystal ball with a precise answer, when it really is forecasting a &lt;mark&gt;wide range of possible outcomes&lt;/mark&gt;.  The report designers on the modeling teams and journalists could both &lt;mark&gt;serve the public better&lt;/mark&gt; by stating the forecast results more carefully as a range rather than as a specific number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;Don't focus too much on the center line&lt;/mark&gt; of the IHME forecast charts, any more than you would assume that a hurricane will follow the center line on the NHC hurricane forecast cone images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bams:cone-of-uncertainty&quot;&gt;1. Broad K, Leiserowitz A, Weinkle J, et al. &lt;b&gt;Misinterpretations of the “Cone of Uncertainty” in Florida during the 2004 Hurricane Season&lt;/b&gt;. American Meterological Society; May-2007 &lt;a href=&quot;https://core.ac.uk/download/pdf/80855756.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-27 16:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wapo:misunderstanding-the-math&quot;&gt;2. Bump P. &lt;b&gt;Misunderstanding the math, Trump embraced a coronavirus death toll we’ll soon surpass&lt;/b&gt;. 24-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.msn.com/en-us/news/politics/misunderstanding-the-math-trump-embraced-a-coronavirus-death-toll-we-ll-soon-surpass/ar-BB136wFd??ocid=twmsn&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-28 9:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wikipedia:false_precision&quot;&gt;3. &lt;b&gt;False precision&lt;/b&gt;. Wikipedia; 17-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/False_precision&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-28 10:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;infowars:virologists-question-lockdowns&quot;&gt;4. Knight D. &lt;b&gt;Virologists &amp;amp; Epidemiologists Question COVID Lockdowns&lt;/b&gt;. Infowars; 21-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infowars.com/watch/?video=5e9f3cdf58b1e9001ff9a14a&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-27 21:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wikipedia:significant_figures&quot;&gt;5. &lt;b&gt;Significant figures&lt;/b&gt;. Wikipedia; 24-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Significant_figures&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-28 10:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/29/dont-focus-on-the-center-line.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/29/dont-focus-on-the-center-line.html</guid>
            
            <category>covid19-models</category>
            
            <category>ihme-model</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Visualizing the cost of COVID-19 in the US</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to visualize the cost that COVID-19 has already had.  The designers of the Vietnam Veterans Memorial designed it partly as a tool for visualizing the same number of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of it is sobering.  That’s what the designers intended.  “Fifty-eight thousand” is an abstraction, but the &lt;mark&gt;58,320 names&lt;/mark&gt; inscribed on the Vietnam Veterans Memorial in Washington DC are an &lt;mark&gt;overwhelming message&lt;/mark&gt; about the cost of the war in Vietnam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-576-b36a66.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-768-b36a66.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-992-b36a66.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-1152-b36a66.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-1536-b36a66.webp 1536w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-1984-b36a66.webp 1984w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-1200-b36a66.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-2400-b36a66.webp 2400w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-576-b36a66.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-768-b36a66.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-992-b36a66.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-1152-b36a66.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-1536-b36a66.jpg 1536w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-1984-b36a66.jpg 1984w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-1200-b36a66.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-2400-b36a66.jpg 2400w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-3-16_9-800-b36a66.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Vietnam Veterans Memorial, credit: Ron Cogswell&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-memorial-as-a-visualization-tool&quot;&gt;A memorial as a visualization tool&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The memorial is so large that it’s difficult to photograph the entire thing.  That’s part of the message.  A mountain of names, where every one was a human life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-576-d0d413.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-768-d0d413.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-992-d0d413.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-1152-d0d413.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-1536-d0d413.webp 1536w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-1984-d0d413.webp 1984w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-1200-d0d413.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-2400-d0d413.webp 2400w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-576-d0d413.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-768-d0d413.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-992-d0d413.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-1152-d0d413.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-1536-d0d413.jpg 1536w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-1984-d0d413.jpg 1984w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-1200-d0d413.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-2400-d0d413.jpg 2400w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-memorial-2-16_5-800-d0d413.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Vietnam Veterans Memorial, credit: Bernt Rostad&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;COVID-19 has claimed as many American lives&lt;/mark&gt;.  Now we’re trying to figure out how to count them, as we debate whether or not to count deaths from people who were believed to have had the coronavirus, like more than five thousand in New York.  As the official death count gallops past fifty thousand, we can be certain that the number of American deaths has &lt;mark&gt;already exceeded&lt;/mark&gt; the body count of the entire ten-year war in Vietnam.  In only a few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vietnams-covid-19-response&quot;&gt;Vietnam’s COVID-19 response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That brings us to today’s Vietnam, during the COVID-19 pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impact of COVID-19 in Vietnam is a striking counterexample from the US.  Vietnam has &lt;mark&gt;not recorded a single death&lt;/mark&gt; from COVID-19, since their first recorded case on January 24.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#thenation:vietnam&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  At the start of the crisis, Vietnam promptly started a system of testing, tracing, and isolating cases.  When the number of cases began to increase, they also closed their borders.  The country’s military, entire public sector, and media industry all worked together to coordinate an early two-week precautionary social-distancing campaign.  Vietnam began to lift restrictions on April 23.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#latimes:vietnam-lifting-restrictions&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/vietnam-cases.jpg&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-cases-576-f5a5d2.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-cases-745-f5a5d2.webp 745w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-cases-576-f5a5d2.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/vietnam-cases-745-f5a5d2.jpg 745w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/vietnam-cases-745-f5a5d2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;2020 coronavirus pandemic in Vietnam, credit: Wikipedia&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic is not over for them yet, but they have bought themselves precious time and used it well, and at least until now they have limited the impact.  Vietnam’s response to COVID-19 has perhaps been the &lt;mark&gt;most successful of any country in the world&lt;/mark&gt;, so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;thenation:vietnam&quot;&gt;1. &lt;b&gt;Vietnam May Have the Most Effective Response to Covid-19&lt;/b&gt;. The Nation; 24-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenation.com/article/world/coronavirus-vietnam-quarantine-mobilization/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-28 17:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;latimes:vietnam-lifting-restrictions&quot;&gt;2. &lt;b&gt;Without a single COVID-19 death, Vietnam starts easing its coronavirus lockdown&lt;/b&gt;. The LA Times; 23-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/world-nation/story/2020-04-23/vietnam-eases-coronavirus-lockdown&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-28 17:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/28/more-us-deaths-to-covid-than-to-vietnam-war.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/28/more-us-deaths-to-covid-than-to-vietnam-war.html</guid>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>It's not The Peak, it's This Peak</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;The widely-cited IHME model does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; forecast that the COVID-19 epidemic will peak&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people are misinterpreting the COVID-19 &lt;a href=&quot;/ihme-model.html&quot;&gt;forecast model&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Washington’s Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-key-misunderstanding&quot;&gt;One key misunderstanding&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a widespread misunderstanding at the heart of almost all of the misinformation related to the IHME model: &lt;mark&gt;Many people think that the IHME model is predicting 'when the epidemic will peak' and then subside before it's all over&lt;/mark&gt;.  But that’s not what the model is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forecast charts from the model seem easy to understand: They show one big hump.  So that means that the models predicts that the infection will be one wave and then over, right?  No, it just means that forecasting future waves of COVID-19 outbreaks is beyond the scope of the model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-peak&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;THIS&lt;/em&gt; peak&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IHME model is not projecting that the epidemic will peak and subside and then it will all be over.  It’s &lt;mark&gt;projecting when the &lt;i&gt;first wave&lt;/i&gt; will peak&lt;/mark&gt;, assuming that social distancing stays in place.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ihme:forecasting-the-impact-of-the-first-wave&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  It’s a planning tool for health planners and governments to project how long before social distancing could be relaxed after &lt;em&gt;one wave&lt;/em&gt; of the epidemic.  It’s not a crystal ball that’s predicting what will happen with the overall pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projecting that first wave is incredibly difficult because exponential growth curves can lead to wildly different outcomes from tiny tweaks in the input parameters.  Trying to model future outbreaks would be even more difficult and unreliable at this point, and so the IHME researchers are not even trying to do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
It is critical to note that &lt;mark&gt;we restrict our projections to the first wave&lt;/mark&gt; of the pandemic under a scenario of continued implementation of social distancing mandates and &lt;mark&gt;do not yet incorporate the possibility of a resurgence&lt;/mark&gt; or subsequent waves.
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ihme:forecasting-the-impact-of-the-first-wave&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Forecasting the impact of the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic on hospital demand and deaths for the USA and European Economic Area countries&lt;/b&gt;. IHME COVID-19 health service utilization forecasting team; 21-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healthdata.org/sites/default/files/files/Projects/COVID/RA_COVID-forecasting-USA-EEA_042120.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-27 16:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that the widely-cited dashboard for the model’s forecasts is not clear about this crucial background information about the model.  Giving people an easily-accessible dashboard that they can easily misunderstand could potentially backfire.  In the worst case, &lt;mark&gt;people will misinterpret the IHME model's reports&lt;/mark&gt; as saying that the threat of COVID-19 is over, and that it’s okay to stop the social distancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The IHME model is not forecasting when the COVID-19 epidemic will be over.  It isn’t forecasting that there will only be one peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s only trying to estimate the timing of the &lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt; wave of the epidemic.  It assumes that we have taken measures to slow the spread of the virus.  And it estimates how long it might take to reduce the number of new infections to a level where social distancing could end.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#ihme:faq&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;  Temporarily.  Future outbreaks would require a repeat of the whole mitigation cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ihme:forecasting-the-impact-of-the-first-wave&quot;&gt;1. &lt;b&gt;Forecasting the impact of the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic on hospital demand and deaths for the USA and European Economic Area countries&lt;/b&gt;. IHME COVID-19 health service utilization forecasting team; 21-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healthdata.org/sites/default/files/files/Projects/COVID/RA_COVID-forecasting-USA-EEA_042120.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-27 16:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ihme:faq&quot;&gt;2. &lt;b&gt;IHME COVID-19 model FAQs&lt;/b&gt;. Institute for Health Metrics and Evaluation; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healthdata.org/covid/faqs&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/27/its-not-the-peak-its-this-peak.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/27/its-not-the-peak-its-this-peak.html</guid>
            
            <category>covid19-models</category>
            
            <category>ihme-model</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The computer forecast model that changed the world</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;No report from any forecast model has ever had such a significant impact on worldwide human society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis at Imperial College of London has arguably created one
of the most influential computer forecasting models in history.  Never before
has one report from one computer model had such a significant impact on human
society as this model did in March 2020.  Their work informs advisory groups
for the government, and during the week of March 9, 2020, preliminary results
from one of their reports alarmed officials and changed the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers had been trying to warn governments that there would be trouble,&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#lancet:warning-to-governments&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; but
the Trump Administration was
reluctant to address the threat directly.  The British government took notice
when the Imperial College model &lt;mark&gt;projected that COVID-19 patients would overrun
their national health care system&lt;/mark&gt;, and nearly immediately
began restrictions.  They notified their counterparts in the US government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened next impacted every American.  By the end of the week of
March 9, the &lt;mark&gt;United States had declared a national emergency&lt;/mark&gt;.  Many areas
like here in Miami Beach closed all restaurants and other non-essential businesses
and went into a shutdown.  The US stocks markets began &lt;mark&gt;one of the biggest
crashes in history&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wikipedia:2020_stock_market_crash&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, leading to a recession dubbed “&lt;mark&gt;The Great Lockdown&lt;/mark&gt;.”&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wikipedia:coronavirus_recession&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;
It was the &lt;mark&gt;steepest economic downturn since the Great Depression&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this from one report from one forecasting model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure inset pull-right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
  &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-576-a21643.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-768-a21643.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-992-a21643.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-1152-a21643.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-1536-a21643.webp 1536w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-1984-a21643.webp 1984w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-1200-a21643.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-2400-a21643.webp 2400w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-576-a21643.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-768-a21643.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-992-a21643.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-1152-a21643.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-1536-a21643.jpg 1536w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-1984-a21643.jpg 1984w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-1200-a21643.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-2400-a21643.jpg 2400w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/neil-ferguson-800-a21643.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/picture&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption text-right small&quot;&gt;UK epidemiologist Neil Ferguson. Credit: Imperial College London&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mathematical modeling team led by Professor Neil Ferguson and Dr Samir Bhatt
has been tracking COVID-19 since the start of the outbreak.  Their original
findings focused on China.  Ferguson, one of the founders of the MRC Centre for
Global Infectious Disease Analysis at Imperial College, was already one of the
leading names in the field of epidemiological modeling.  He had previously
worked on modeling BSE/vCJD, foot and mouth disease, SARS and MERS, pandemic influenza, Ebola and Zika.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#imperial-college:neil-ferguson&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mid-January, he &lt;mark&gt;took an existing model built in 2005 to study H5N1 avian
flu and adapted its assumptions to model SARS-CoV-2&lt;/mark&gt;.  He and his team worked on
a report examining the projected impact of the epidemic in different countries
based on their economic level, and the potential life-saving effects of
social distancing.  He didn’t get a day off from that point until mid-March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news in their report was not necessarily that COVID-19 could kill a lot of
people.  The report doesn’t even speculate about the final death count, it only
focuses on the near term.  What the Imperial College report added was the
&lt;mark&gt;analysis of the potential cost of not
taking measures to slow the spread of the infection&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#imperial-college:global-impact&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart.png&quot;&gt;
  &lt;picture&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-576-079a41.webp 576w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-768-079a41.webp 768w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-992-079a41.webp 992w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-1152-079a41.webp 1152w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-1200-079a41.webp 1200w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-1534-079a41.webp 1534w&quot; type=&quot;image/webp&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source sizes=&quot;(max-width: 768px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 992px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), (max-width: 1200px) calc(25vw - 1.5rem*2), calc(100vw - 1.5rem*2)&quot; srcset=&quot;/generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-576-079a41.jpg 576w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-768-079a41.jpg 768w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-992-079a41.jpg 992w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-1152-079a41.jpg 1152w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-1200-079a41.jpg 1200w, /generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-1534-079a41.jpg 1534w&quot; type=&quot;image/jpeg&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/generated/images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-800-079a41.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;

  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Chart from Imperial College report showing the potential life-saving effects of social distancing.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report is especially relevant now in April, as society faces a crisis of
discipline in maintaining social distancing.  For example, the above chart
from their report &lt;mark&gt;predicts a second wave after suppression strategies are
lifted after three months&lt;/mark&gt;.  Some quotes from the paper seem as prophetic now,
a month later, as one would hope from a report from a forecasting team:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
We do not consider the wider social and economic costs of suppression, which will be high and may be disproportionately so in lower income settings. Moreover, &lt;mark&gt;suppression strategies will need to be maintained in some manner until vaccines or effective treatments become available to avoid the risk of later epidemics&lt;/mark&gt;. Our analysis highlights the challenging decisions faced by all governments in the coming weeks and months, but demonstrates the extent to which &lt;mark&gt;rapid, decisive and collective action now could save millions of lives&lt;/mark&gt;.
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-college:global-impact&quot;&gt;Walker PGT, Whittaker C, Watson O, et al. &lt;b&gt;Report 12: The Global Impact of COVID-19 and Strategies for Mitigation and Suppression&lt;/b&gt;. Imperial College London - MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis; 26-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/mrc-gida/2020-03-26-COVID19-Report-12.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;; DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.25561/77735&quot;&gt;10.25561/77735&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-19 11:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;mark&gt;The timing amplified the impact of the report&lt;/mark&gt;.  As Ferguson was briefing
UK government officials, they were hearing from terrified colleagues in Italy
who were realizing how many COVID-19 patients were going to require invasive
ventilation in ICUs.  The report may have been the final straw that resulted
in a “&lt;mark&gt;sudden focusing of minds&lt;/mark&gt;”, according to Ferguson.  The UK government
had suddenly become more receptive to imposing social distancing, and the US
wasn’t far behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just two days after briefing officials in Downing Street, Ferguson’s own
symptoms started.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#nature:covid19-simulations&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;  He had &lt;mark&gt;contracted the same COVID-19 disease&lt;/mark&gt; that he had
spent months modeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Sigh. Developed a slight dry but persistent cough yesterday and self isolated even though I felt fine. Then developed high fever at 4am today. There is a lot of COVID-19 in Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; neil_ferguson (@neil_ferguson) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/neil_ferguson/status/1240171876695117824?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferguson is feeling better now, but he’s facing increasing scrutiny for what
might be the biggest weakness of the Imperial College model: a lack of
transparency.  Ideally, a model should have documented, open source code
that’s portable enough for other people to run it and reproduce your results.
At a bare minimum, researchers should document their assumptions, input
parameters, and methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite promising a month ago on March 22 that he was working with Micosoft and
GitHub to release the code for the model, &lt;mark&gt;Ferguson still has not posted anything on GitHub&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Still no sign of the code for one of the most impactful simulations ever created. From morsels in older papers there are tens of input parameters, C and OpenMP with multi-hour runs. A month lost helping others understand and build on it, straight up bad science. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/Hsvk9kHDtk&quot;&gt;https://t.co/Hsvk9kHDtk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; James Grogan (@JmsGrogan) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JmsGrogan/status/1251763035267620865?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferguson said that the code is dirty and undocumented and needs refactoring work,
but nobody expects it to be perfect.  He should post the source code as-is,
and then push updates as he refactors the code to improve it.  Science shouldn’t
have to wait for him to clean up his code before learning from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;lancet:warning-to-governments&quot;&gt;1. &lt;b&gt;How will country-based mitigation measures influence the course of the COVID-19 epidemic?&lt;/b&gt; The Lancet; 20-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)30567-5/fulltext&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-20 19:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wikipedia:2020_stock_market_crash&quot;&gt;2. &lt;b&gt;2020 stock market crash&lt;/b&gt;. Wikipedia; 20-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2020_stock_market_crash&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-20 12:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wikipedia:coronavirus_recession&quot;&gt;3. &lt;b&gt;Coronavirus recession&lt;/b&gt;. Wikipedia; 20-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coronavirus_recession&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-20 12:00) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-college:neil-ferguson&quot;&gt;4. &lt;b&gt;Professor Neil Ferguson - Faculty of Medicine, School of Public Health&lt;/b&gt;. Imperial College London - MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/neil.ferguson&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-20 19:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-college:global-impact&quot;&gt;5. Walker PGT, Whittaker C, Watson O, et al. &lt;b&gt;Report 12: The Global Impact of COVID-19 and Strategies for Mitigation and Suppression&lt;/b&gt;. Imperial College London - MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis; 26-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/mrc-gida/2020-03-26-COVID19-Report-12.pdf&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;; DOI: &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.25561/77735&quot;&gt;10.25561/77735&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-19 11:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;nature:covid19-simulations&quot;&gt;6. &lt;b&gt;Special report: The simulations driving the world’s response to COVID-19&lt;/b&gt;. Nature; 2-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-01003-6&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-20 19:30) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/20/the-computer-forecast-model-that-changed-the-world.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/20/the-computer-forecast-model-that-changed-the-world.html</guid>
            
            <category>covid19-models</category>
            
            <category>imperial-college-model</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Nearly a third of people in a town near Boston tested positive for antibodies</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;People stopped randomly in public for antibody tests showed a surprising infection proportion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers in Santa Clara County in California recently found about 2.5% to 4.2% of randomly-selected people tested positive for antibodies.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#abc:caantibodysurprise&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  But their methods have been criticized because their sample may have been biased toward people who thought they might have been infected and were seeking a way to be tested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new study in Boston showed an even higher percentage of positive antibody tests, and from a better sample.  &lt;mark&gt;Nearly a third of 200 blood samples taken from people in Chelsea, a town across the river from Boston, tested positive.&lt;/mark&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#bostonglobe:athirdinchelsea&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;  The researchers avoided bias toward people who wanted to be tested, by not announcing the sample collection in advance and randomly walking up to people in a town square and asking them to volunteer.  The volunteers were not offered results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea has been hit hard by the pandemic because of two factors.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#bostonglobe:whychelsea&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;  It is &lt;mark&gt;one of the most dense places in Massachusetts.  And it's also a working-class neighborhood, with residents working in essential sectors&lt;/mark&gt; like food establishments and engaged with high levels of public interaction like healthcare and personal services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking up to random people in public with no warning does avoid bias toward people who wanted to be tested.  But it also had the effect of biasing the sample toward people who were walking around in public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big variation between the Santa Clara study and the Chelsea study show that we need many more studies like this to learn how widespread SARS-CoV-2 infections really are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until that starts to happen here, statistical methods are the best way that we have for estimating how widespread the virus is right now.  Here’s the current best estimate, as of this writing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  
    &lt;img class=&quot;img-fluid&quot; src=&quot;/charts/projected-percentage-of-sarscov2-infections/miami-beach/2020-04-18-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;
  
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;abc:caantibodysurprise&quot;&gt;1. Ng C, Abdelmalek DM. &lt;b&gt;Antibody research indicates coronavirus may be far more widespread than known&lt;/b&gt;. ABC News; 17-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcnews.go.com/Health/antibody-research-coronavirus-widespread/story?id=70206121&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-17 17:20) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bostonglobe:athirdinchelsea&quot;&gt;2. Saltzman J. &lt;b&gt;Nearly a third of 200 blood samples taken in Chelsea show exposure to coronavirus&lt;/b&gt;. The Boston Globe; 17-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bostonglobe.com/2020/04/17/business/nearly-third-200-blood-samples-taken-chelsea-show-exposure-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-18 19:20) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bostonglobe:whychelsea&quot;&gt;3. DeCosta-Klipa N. &lt;b&gt;Why the city of Chelsea has been so hard hit by coronavirus&lt;/b&gt;. The Boston Globe; 10-April-2020 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boston.com/news/local-news/2020/04/10/chelsea-massachusetts-coronavirus&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2020-04-18 19:45) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 19:20:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/18/nearly-a-third-of-people-in-town-near-boston-have-antibodies.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://0.0.0.0:4000/2020/04/18/nearly-a-third-of-people-in-town-near-boston-have-antibodies.html</guid>
            
            <category>how-widespread</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
