<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title></title>
        <description>Intended as a documentation theme based on Jekyll for technical writers documenting software and other technical products, this theme has all the elements you would need to handle multiple products with both multi-level sidebar navigation, tags, and other documentation features.</description>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 15:16:10 -0400</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 15:16:10 -0400</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>
        
        <item>
            <title>The computer forecast model that changed the world</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;The MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis at Imperial College of London has arguably created one
of the most influential computer forecasting models in history.  Never before
has one report from one computer model had such a significant impact on human
society as this model did in March 2020.  Their work informs advisory groups
for the government, and during the week of March 9, 2020, preliminary results
from a report raised an alarm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers had been trying to warn governments that there would be trouble,
&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#lancet:warning-to-governments&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; but The Trump Administration was
reluctant to address the threat directly.  The British government took notice
when the Imperial College model projected that COVID-19 patients would overrun
their national health care system would be overrun, and nearly immediately
began restrictions.  They notified their counterparts in the US government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened next impacted every American.  By the end of the week of
March 9, the United States had declared a national emergency.  Many areas
like here in Miami Beach closed all restaurants and other non-essential businesses
and went into a shutdown.  The US stocks markets began one of the biggest
crashes in history,&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wikipedia:2020_stock_market_crash&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; leading to a
recession dubbed the “Great Lockdown.”&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#wikipedia:coronavirus_recession&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;
It was the steepest economic downturn since the Great Depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this from one report from one forecasting model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure inset pull-right&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/assets/resized/neil-ferguson-1600x1600.png&quot; alt=&quot;UK epidemiologist Neil Ferguson.Credit: Imperial College London&quot; srcset=&quot;    /assets/resized/neil-ferguson-480x480.png 480w,    /assets/resized/neil-ferguson-768x768.png 768w,    /assets/resized/neil-ferguson-992x992.png 992w,    /assets/resized/neil-ferguson-1200x1200.png 1200w,    /assets/resized/neil-ferguson-1600x1600.png 1600w, /images/posts/neil-ferguson.png 3132w&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption text-right small&quot;&gt;UK epidemiologist Neil Ferguson.Credit: Imperial College London&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mathematical modeling team led by Professor Neil Ferguson and Dr Samir Bhatt
has been tracking COVID-19 since the start of the outbreak.  Their original
findings focused on China.  Ferguson, one of the founders of the MRC Centre for
Global Infectious Disease Analysis at Imperial College, was already one of the
leading names in the field of epidemiological modeling.  He had previously
worked on modeling BSE/vCJD, foot and mouth disease, SARS and MERS, pandemic influenza, Ebola and Zika.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#imperial-college:neil-ferguson&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mid-January, he took an existing model built in 2005 to study H5N1 avian
flu and adapted its assumptions to model SARS-CoV-2.  He and his team worked on
a report examining the projected impact of the epidemic in different countries
based on their economic level, and the potential life-saving effects of
social distancing.  He didn’t get a day off from that point until mid-March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The news in their report was not necessarily that COVID-19 could kill a lot of
people.  The report doesn’t even speculate about the final death count, it only
focuses on the near term.  What the Imperial College report added was the
analysis of the potential cost of not
mitigating.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#imperial-college:global-impact&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; src=&quot;/assets/resized/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-1200x743.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chart from Imperial College report showing the potential
  life-saving effects of social distancing.&quot; srcset=&quot;    /assets/resized/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-480x297.png 480w,    /assets/resized/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-768x476.png 768w,    /assets/resized/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-992x614.png 992w,    /assets/resized/imperial-college-mitigation-chart-1200x743.png 1200w, /images/posts/imperial-college-mitigation-chart.png 1534w&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class=&quot;figure-caption small&quot;&gt;Chart from Imperial College report showing the potential
  life-saving effects of social distancing.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report is especially relevant now in April, as society faces a crisis of
discipline in maintaining social distancing.  For example, the above chart
from their report predicts a second wave after suppression strategies are
lifted after three months.  Some quotes from the paper seem as prophetic now,
a month later, as one would hope from a report from a forecasting team:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;blockquote&quot;&gt;
We do not consider the wider social and economic costs of suppression, which will be high and may be disproportionately so in lower income settings. Moreover, suppression strategies will need to be maintained in some manner until vaccines or effective treatments become available to avoid the risk of later epidemics. Our analysis highlights the challenging decisions faced by all governments in the coming weeks and months, but demonstrates the extent to which rapid, decisive and collective action now could save millions of lives.
&lt;footer&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-college:global-impact&quot;&gt;Report 12: The Global Impact of COVID-19 and Strategies for Mitigation and Suppression. April 26, 2020 [cited 2020-04-19 11:30]; Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/mrc-gida/2020-03-26-COVID19-Report-12.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/mrc-gida/2020-03-26-COVID19-Report-12.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The timing amplified the impact of the report.  As Ferguson was briefing
UK government officials, they were hearing from terrified colleagues in Italy
who were realizing how many COVID-19 patients were going to require invasive
ventilation in ICUs.  The report may have been the final straw that resulted
in a “sudden focusing of minds”, according to Ferguson.  The UK government
had suddenly become more receptive to imposing social distancing, and the US
wasn’t far behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just two days after briefing officials in Downing Street, Ferguson’s own
symptoms started.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#nature:covid19-simulations&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;  He had contracted the same COVID-19 disease that he had
spent months modeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Sigh. Developed a slight dry but persistent cough yesterday and self isolated even though I felt fine. Then developed high fever at 4am today. There is a lot of COVID-19 in Westminster.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; neil_ferguson (@neil_ferguson) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/neil_ferguson/status/1240171876695117824?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferguson is feeling better now, but he’s facing increasing scrutiny for what
might be the biggest weakness of the Imperial College model: a lack of
transparency.  Ideally, a model should have documented, open source code
that’s portable enough for other people to run it and reproduce your results.
At a bare minimum, researchers should document their assumptions, input
parameters, and methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite promising a month ago on March 22 that he was working with Micosoft and
GitHub to release the code for the model, Ferguson still has not posted anything
on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Still no sign of the code for one of the most impactful simulations ever created. From morsels in older papers there are tens of input parameters, C and OpenMP with multi-hour runs. A month lost helping others understand and build on it, straight up bad science. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/Hsvk9kHDtk&quot;&gt;https://t.co/Hsvk9kHDtk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; James Grogan (@JmsGrogan) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JmsGrogan/status/1251763035267620865?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 19, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferguson said that the code is dirty and undocumented and needs refactoring work,
but nobody expects it to be perfect.  He should post the source code as-is,
and then push updates as he refactors the code to improve it.  Science shouldn’t
have to wait for him to clean up his code before learning from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;lancet:warning-to-governments&quot;&gt;1. How will country-based mitigation measures influence the course of the COVID-19 epidemic? April 20, 2020 [cited 2020-04-20 19:00]; Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)30567-5/fulltext&quot;&gt;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)30567-5/fulltext&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wikipedia:2020_stock_market_crash&quot;&gt;2. 2020 stock market crash. April 20, 2020 [cited 2020-04-20 12:00]; Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2020_stock_market_crash&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2020_stock_market_crash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;wikipedia:coronavirus_recession&quot;&gt;3. Coronavirus recession. April 20, 2020 [cited 2020-04-20 12:00]; Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coronavirus_recession&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coronavirus_recession&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-college:neil-ferguson&quot;&gt;4. Special report: The simulations driving the world’s response to COVID-19 [Internet]. Imperial College London - MRC Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis; [cited 2020-04-20 19:30]. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/neil.ferguson&quot;&gt;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/people/neil.ferguson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;imperial-college:global-impact&quot;&gt;5. Report 12: The Global Impact of COVID-19 and Strategies for Mitigation and Suppression. April 26, 2020 [cited 2020-04-19 11:30]; Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/mrc-gida/2020-03-26-COVID19-Report-12.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/medicine/mrc-gida/2020-03-26-COVID19-Report-12.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;nature:covid19-simulations&quot;&gt;6. Special report: The simulations driving the world’s response to COVID-19. April 2, 2020 [cited 2020-04-20 19:30]; Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-01003-6&quot;&gt;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-01003-6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/20/the-computer-forecast-model-that-changed-the-world.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/04/20/the-computer-forecast-model-that-changed-the-world.html</guid>
            
            <category>covid19-models</category>
            
            <category>imperial-college-model</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Nearly a third of people in a town near Boston have antibodies</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Researchers in Santa Clara County in California recently found about 2.5% to 4.2% of randomly-selected people tested positive for antibodies.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#abc:caantibodysurprise&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  But their methods have been criticized because their sample may have been biased toward people who thought they might have been infected and were seeking a way to be tested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new study in Boston showed an even higher percentage of positive antibody tests, and from a better sample.  Nearly a third of 200 blood samples taken from people in Chelsea, a town across the river from Boston, tested positive.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#bostonglobe:athirdinchelsea&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;  The researchers avoided bias toward people who wanted to be tested, by not announcing the sample collection in advance and randomly walking up to people in a town square and asking them to volunteer.  The volunteers were not offered results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea has been hit hard by the pandemic because of two factors.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#bostonglobe:whychelsea&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;  It is one of the most dense places in Massachusetts.  And it’s also a working-class neighborhood, with residents working in essential sectors like food establishments and engaged with high levels of public interaction like healthcare and personal services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking up to random people in public with no warning does avoid bias toward people who wanted to be tested.  But it also had the effect of biasing the sample toward people who were walking around in public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big variation between the Santa Clara study and the Chelsea study show that we need many more studies like this to learn how widespread SARS-CoV-2 infections really are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until that starts to happen here, statistical methods are the best way that we have for estimating how widespread the virus is right now.  Here’s the current best estimate, as of this writing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/projected-percentage-of-sarscov2-infections/miami-beach/2020-04-18-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;abc:caantibodysurprise&quot;&gt;1. Ng C, Abdelmalek DM. Antibody research indicates coronavirus may be far more widespread than known [Internet]. ABC News; 2020 [cited 2020-04-17 17:20]. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcnews.go.com/Health/antibody-research-coronavirus-widespread/story?id=70206121&quot;&gt;https://abcnews.go.com/Health/antibody-research-coronavirus-widespread/story?id=70206121&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bostonglobe:athirdinchelsea&quot;&gt;2. Saltzman J. Nearly a third of 200 blood samples taken in Chelsea show exposure to coronavirus [Internet]. The Boston Globe; 2020 [cited 2020-04-18 19:20]. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bostonglobe.com/2020/04/17/business/nearly-third-200-blood-samples-taken-chelsea-show-exposure-coronavirus/&quot;&gt;https://www.bostonglobe.com/2020/04/17/business/nearly-third-200-blood-samples-taken-chelsea-show-exposure-coronavirus/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;bostonglobe:whychelsea&quot;&gt;3. DeCosta-Klipa N. Why the city of Chelsea has been so hard hit by coronavirus [Internet]. The Boston Globe; 2020 [cited 2020-04-18 19:45]. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boston.com/news/local-news/2020/04/10/chelsea-massachusetts-coronavirus&quot;&gt;https://www.boston.com/news/local-news/2020/04/10/chelsea-massachusetts-coronavirus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Sat, 18 Apr 2020 19:20:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/18/nearly-a-third-of-people-in-town-near-boston-have-antibodies.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/04/18/nearly-a-third-of-people-in-town-near-boston-have-antibodies.html</guid>
            
            <category>how-widespread</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>New antibody research is consistent with the estimates here for number of infections</title>
            <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-many-people-have-been-infected-with-sars-cov-2&quot;&gt;How many people have been infected with SARS-CoV-2?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to estimate the number of infections is from the number of confirmed cases.  Mathematical modelers in the Centre for the Mathematical Modelling of Infectious Diseases (CMMID) at the London School of Hygiene &amp;amp; Tropical Medicine maintain a model for estimating an approximate fraction of cases reported.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#cmmid&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;  They update their model nearly daily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of this writing, that model estimates that only 12% of cases in the US are reported.  With a 95% confidence range from 11% to 26%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying that to the numbers for Miami Beach as of this writing, if the 607 confirmed cases for Miami Beach represent 12% of infections, then the real number of infections would be about 5,058.  With a Miami Beach population estimate of 91,718, about 5.5% of people here could be infected.  (From 2.5% to 6% in the 95% confidence range.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here that is in a chart, to show how it has been rising fast over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/estimated-number-of-sarscov2-infections-as-percentage-of-population/miami-beach/2020-04-17-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But can’t we measure it directly?  Yes, now we can test for antibodies, to determine if a person has ever been infected.  And the first studies that use antibody testing are consistent with the estimates based on the number of confirmed cases.  Two research teams in California are testing large numbers of people with the new antibody tests.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#abc:caantibodysurprise&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;&quot;The first large-scale community test of 3,300 people in Santa Clara County found that 2.5 to 4.2% of those tested were positive for antibodies.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#abc:caantibodysurprise&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing the infection percentage estimates between Santa Clara County, California to Miami Beach without adjusting for the population size and confirmed case count is comparing apples to oranges.  But the 2.5% to 4.2% range from the antibody tests in California falls right into the estimated range for Miami Beach.  This makes the estimates for our area that are based on the CMMID range seem roughly plausible.  It’s some of the best information that we have until we get data from widespread antibody tests here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-then-what-about-herd-immunity&quot;&gt;So then what about herd immunity?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experts estimate the critical threshold for reaching herd immunity against SARS-CoV-2 to be about 50% to 66%.&lt;a class=&quot;citation&quot; href=&quot;#abc:herdimmunityrange&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;  If those estimates for the percentage of people infected seem plausible, then what do they tell us about how close we are to reaching herd immunity?  Unfortunately, we’re still a long way from that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the chart above, basically zoomed out to show how long it would take to reach the critical herd immunity threshold (shaded green) at the current rate.  (Assuming a linear spread, which seems unlikely given the current political environment.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/projected-percentage-of-sarscov2-infections/miami-beach/2020-04-17-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-wider-areas&quot;&gt;What about wider areas?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we look outward from Miami Beach, the percentage of the population infected in Miami is larger, according to the CMMID estimation method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/estimated-number-of-sarscov2-infections-as-percentage-of-population/miami/2020-04-17-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/projected-percentage-of-sarscov2-infections/miami/2020-04-17-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for Florida overall, the percentage may be lower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/estimated-number-of-sarscov2-infections-as-percentage-of-population/florida/2020-04-17-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/projected-percentage-of-sarscov2-infections/florida/2020-04-17-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the percentage of the population who has been infected really that much lower for larger Florida than it is for Miami?  We’ll know more as antibody testing becomes more widespread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;cmmid&quot;&gt;1. Using a delay-adjusted case fatality ratio to estimate under-reporting [Internet]. Centre for the Mathematical Modelling of Infectious Diseases at the London School of Hygiene &amp;amp; Tropical Medicine; 2020 [cited 2020-04-17 19:30]. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cmmid.github.io/topics/covid19/severity/global_cfr_estimates.html&quot;&gt;https://cmmid.github.io/topics/covid19/severity/global_cfr_estimates.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;abc:caantibodysurprise&quot;&gt;2. Ng C, Abdelmalek DM. Antibody research indicates coronavirus may be far more widespread than known [Internet]. ABC News; 2020 [cited 2020-04-17 17:20]. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcnews.go.com/Health/antibody-research-coronavirus-widespread/story?id=70206121&quot;&gt;https://abcnews.go.com/Health/antibody-research-coronavirus-widespread/story?id=70206121&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;abc:herdimmunityrange&quot;&gt;3. Bruggeman L. As some leaders weigh pursuit of ‘herd immunity’ from coronavirus, experts warn risks are too high [Internet]. ABC News; 2020 [cited 2020-04-17 20:20]. Available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcnews.go.com/Health/leaders-weigh-pursuit-herd-immunity-experts-warn-risks/story?id=70072952&quot;&gt;https://abcnews.go.com/Health/leaders-weigh-pursuit-herd-immunity-experts-warn-risks/story?id=70072952&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 18:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/17/estimates-for-percentage-of-population-infected-consistent-with-new-research.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/04/17/estimates-for-percentage-of-population-infected-consistent-with-new-research.html</guid>
            
            <category>how-widespread</category>
            
            <category>herd-immunity</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>FDEM data now available in Google Sheets</title>
            <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem&quot;&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Florida Division of Emergency Management releases their twice-daily updates as PDF files.  The data in those files is not easy to analyze without extracting it into a spreadsheet or a data file.  I have been pulling numbers by hand out of the PDF files into an Excel spreadsheet for analysis.  It’s time-consuming and it delays my updates, and if I take a day off then the visualizations don’t update themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;solution&quot;&gt;Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote some &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/endymion/BeachCov2/tree/master/data&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt; that extracts the city-by-city data from those PDF files into a spreadsheet in Google Sheets.  I can run it periodically to get the latest updates.  Then I can use that spreadsheet directly for visualizations with Google Data Studio, or I can transform the data to other spreadsheets with Ruby or R for further analysis and use those spreadsheets in visualizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1us_aePT2_OQoc3iBXckrBAeYZb8j4bVAY_cr8t6V8r0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;the spreadsheet&lt;/a&gt; public, and I’ll update it with each new FDEM update:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe style=&quot;width:100%;&quot; height=&quot;500px&quot; src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/e/2PACX-1vTs88ZRLrHIs9YQyzyhuONV7lQfpGB6Y0KhmkfkJNpnYkcGMW2jOSyjXSabu3iUYyVnI8-hWajTXES_/pubhtml?widget=true&amp;amp;headers=false&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that I have so far is the city-by-city data, but that’s a start.  Next I’ll add the county-level data to another Google Sheets spreadsheet, and then also the Florida-wide data..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently not using the case-by-case data in the FDEM reports, and I don’t have any plans to extract that data.  Please contact me if you need that data in machine-readable form and it might help you if I did extract it.  I’d be happy to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have to run this each time, but I designed all of the code to run in AWS Lambda.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/17/FEDM-data-in-Google-Sheets.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/04/17/FEDM-data-in-Google-Sheets.html</guid>
            
            <category>meta</category>
            
            <category>data-engineering</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Are we there yet?</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;If our plan, by default, is herd immunity, then are we there yet?  Are there yet?  Are we there yet?  Check our progress any time here at https://BeachCov2.info/charts  I’m still adding analysis products to the web site.  The newest is the percentage infected projection chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please see the
  &lt;a href=&quot;/products/projected-percentage-of-sarscov2-infections/&quot;&gt;Current
    SARS-CoV-2 Infection Percentage Projection Charts&lt;/a&gt; analysis product section for
    more information and archives of older versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;
  
  &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/projected-percentage-of-sarscov2-infections/miami/2020-04-17-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2020 17:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/14/are-we-there-yet.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/04/14/are-we-there-yet.html</guid>
            
            <category>how-widespread</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Wider infection estimate range</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;The Centre for Mathematical Modelling of Infectious Diseases at the London School of Hygiene &amp;amp; Tropical Medicine has revised their estimated range for the ratio of overall infections to reported cases. Their range is now a lot wider than it has been over the last week or two. Their estimated range is the best idea that I have for estimating the number of SARS-CoV-2 infections from the number of confirmed COVID-19 cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the uncertainty bands on my &lt;a href=&quot;/products/current_estimated-number-of-sarscov2-infections/current.html&quot;&gt;charts&lt;/a&gt; for the estimated number of infections has gotten a lot wider with the most recent update. The line toward the top of the range is their best estimate that 12% of infections are reported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estimated infection count charts for other areas are available in the
&lt;a href=&quot;/products/current_estimated-number-of-sarscov2-infections/&quot;&gt;Estimated Number of SARS-CoV-2 Infections&lt;/a&gt;
analysis product section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;
  
  &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/estimated-number-of-sarscov2-infections/miami-beach/2020-04-14-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/13/wider-infection-estimate-range.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/04/13/wider-infection-estimate-range.html</guid>
            
            <category>how-widespread</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Dashboard product documentation</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been posting more slowly in the last couple of days because I’ve been
working on a web site for hosting explanations and citations, for showing the
current versions of charts, and for chart archives.  Now I have the section
of the site set up for the &lt;a href=&quot;/products/covid19-dashboard/&quot;&gt;COVID-19 Dashboard&lt;/a&gt;
analysis product.  Here’s the latest, with the new site branding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;
  
  &lt;figure&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;docimage&quot; src=&quot;/charts/covid19-dashboard/miami-beach/2020-04-14-B-evening.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
            <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/04/13/dashboard-product.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/04/13/dashboard-product.html</guid>
            
            <category>meta</category>
            
            
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
